Guide to the Columbia University in World War I Collection
Columbia University Archives
Columbia University in World War I Collection,
1914-1970
Columbia University.
8.92 linear feet (19 document boxes, 1 index card box)
Columbia University. University Archives. New York, NY 10027.
MS#0014
4223520
This collection contains records documenting Columbia University's activities slightly prior to, during and immediately following World War I. The collection consists of mostly correspondence, but also includes newspaper clippings, pamphlets, various publications, reports, photographs, service record cards, and numerous lists of Columbia men and women who served during the war.
Historical Note
The Columbia University community and administration mobilized to the fullest extent in answer to the entry of the United States into World War I. Summed up by President Nicholas Murray Butler in the 1918 Annual Report, the effects of the war on the University were far-reaching: "Students by the hundred and prospective students by the thousand entered the military, naval, or civil service of the United States; teachers and administrative officers to the number of nearly four hundred sought and obtained leaves of absence or resigned their posts in order to enter the service of the Government; courses of instruction were modified or abandoned; habitual modes of procedure were altered; the whole University went upon a war footing." Soon after the nation mobilized in 1917, the war effort consumed Columbia in every way, from installation of new courses and military training on South Field to creating a War Records Committee to record every Columbia community member's participation in the war effort. Columbia's mobilization was so intense that the U.S. government used many of Columbia's programs and efforts as an example for the country's other institutions of higher education.
The first direct military activity on campus was on March 8, 1917 when the Columbia Reserve Officers Training Corps (also known as: Columbia Battalion or Columbia Corps) was formed. Within four months of formation, 1400 had enrolled in the Battalion. In April 1918, the Battalion was disbanded when it was announced, that the Reserve Officers Training Corps (ROTC) would be established to replace it. The ROTC, however, was never realized because the U.S. Army created the Student Army Training Corps to fill its place in the summer of 1918.
In April 1917 the Trustees of the University approved the creation of the Columbia War Hospital, a medical training camp, to be located on a piece of land in the Bronx called the Columbia Oval. Due to fear of naval bombardment, the hospital was also meant to handle victims of these bombardments if they occurred or to handle ill soldiers or war disasters. The War Department took over the Hospital on October 3, 1917 and renamed it the U.S. Army General Hospital Number One. In other war efforts, alumni raised enough money in September 1917 to set up the Ambulance Service Division. In addition, the University established the Columbia Service Bureau, part of the American University Union. Horatio S. Krans (CC 1894) headed the Bureau as "a friendly and helpful port of call for hundreds of Columbia soldiers on leave to Paris." (Fon W. Boardman, Jr., Columbia: An American University in Peace and War, p.47)
The University participated in and created many other programs and facilities to further the war effort, including the emergency training corps; establishment of the Military and Naval Bureau in East Hall; Mobilization Committee for Women's Work which organized women for volunteer and salaried positions; the establishment of the United States Navy Gas Engine School; the inclusion of war-related courses being taught through the Department of Extension Teaching; and the creation of the Farm Bureau.
Scope and Content
This collection contains records documenting Columbia University's activities slightly prior to, during and immediately following World War I. The collection consists of mostly correspondence, but also includes newspaper clippings, pamphlets, various publications, reports, photographs, service record cards, and numerous lists of Columbia men and women who served during the war. Correspondence is mostly with the Office of the Secretary, the War Records Committee and the Alumni Federation Office regarding Columbia faculty, staff, students, and alumni participation in the war effort.
Among the major topics represented in this collection are various alumni activities, including the publication of the Alumni News's military supplements, war records, and war memorials; the work of the Columbia Service Bureau established in France to create a place for service men and women to meet fellow Columbians; the Committee on Women's War Work; various instruction and training facilities and programs including the Student Army Training Corps and the Training Corps for Officers; the War Records Committee; and the Columbia War Hospital.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in eight series.
Series I: Alumni Activities, 1917-1944
Series II: Columbia Service Bureau, 1917-1934
Series III: Columbia War Hospital, 1914-1922
Series IV: Committee on Women's War Work, 1917-1919
Series V: Instruction and Training, 1916-1923
Subseries V.1: General, 1917-1923
Subseries V.2: Student Army Training Corps, 1918
Subseries V.3: Training Corps for Officers, 1916-1917
Series VI.: War Records Committee, 1915-1930
Subseries VI.1: Departments and Schools, 1915-1920
subseries VI.2: Fraternities, 1917-1920
Subseries VI.3: Alumni Classes, 1917-1920
Subseries VI.4: General Correspondence, 1916-1921
Subseries VI.5: War Casualties, 1917-1930
Subseries VI.6: Topics, 1917-1923
Series VII: Wartime Work, 1914-1928
Series VIII: Publications and Clippings, 1914-1970
Subjects
Columbia University; Columbia War Hospital; American University Union in Europe; United States. Army. Coast Artillery Corps, 9th (1917-1922); United States. Army. General Hospital no.1.; United States. Dept. of the Treasury; Université catholique de Louvain (1835-1969). Bibliothéque.; Krans, Horatio Sheafe, 1872-1952; Fackenthal, Frank Diehl, 1883-1968; Academic freedom.; World War, 1914-1918--Study and teaching.; World War, 1914-1918--Women.; World War, 1914-1918--Education and the war.; World War, 1914-1918--War work--Schools.; World War, 1914-1918--Medical care.; World War, 1914-1918--Hospitals, charities, etc.; Lists; Questionnaires; Correspondence; Ephemera; Clippings; Applications; Maps; Photographs
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
Selected Related Materal at Columbia
Central Files, Columbia University, University Archives.
Historial Subject Files, Columbia University, University Archives.
Flat Files, Oversize Collection, Columbia University, University Archives.
Presidential Annual Reports, 1917-1918, Columbia University, University Archives.
Acquisition
Various offices and groups generated this artificial collection, which has been pulled together to represent the varied activities undertaken by the Columbia community during the World War I era. The card file of the Committee on Women's War Work came with the RBML 2002 transfer. Other material in the collection was either part of the 1997 RBML accession.
- Series I: Alumni Activities, 1917-1944
  This series consists of correspondence, articles, and lists regarding the various activities of the Alumni Federation and other alumni groups. During the war, the Alumni News published articles in every issue on Columbia's war work. These issues included military supplements and the war commencement issue of 1917. This series also includes the letters from Horatio Krans of the Columbia Service Bureau in France providing updates on the war effort in Europe. There is brief information on the Alumni Committee on International Affairs and the Alumni Committee on Mobilization. The folder "Alumni War Association of Paris" contains mostly correspondence from Levering Tyson to others regarding the Association and its formation. In addition, the Alumni Federation was instrumental in creating lists for the war memorial and war records as shown in this series. The folder of "War Service Medals, Ribbons and Memorials" contains samples of ribbons the University considered using in developing war service medals and ribbons.
  - Alumni Committee on International Affairs, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alumni Committee on Mobilization, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alumni News
    - Articles
      - ROTC, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Student Army Training Corp., 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - University War Work, 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Columbia at War, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Columbia War Papers, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - First War Commencement, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Horatio Krans Letters, 1917-1920, 1927, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 9 to 10)
    - Military Supplements, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Alumni War Association of Paris, 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ambulance Unit, 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Columbia War Memorial
    - Correspondence and Lists, 1920, 1928-1931, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Proof, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Columbia War Record
    - 1918 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1918-1932, (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 2 to 3)
    - Drafts, circa 1917 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - General Information, 1919, 1930, 1944, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - List of Alumni Who Won Distinction, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - War Service List, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - War Service Medals, Ribbons and Memorials, 1918-1920 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series II: Columbia Service Bureau, 1917-1934
  These records are mostly administrative correspondence regarding the day-to-day maintenance of the Columbia Service Bureau (CSB) as well as correspondence with individuals regarding membership and donations to the Bureau. Most of the correspondence is between Frank Diehl Fackenthal, Secretary of the University, and Horatio Krans, director of the CSB. There is considerable correspondence with Roger Pierce, Secretary of Harvard University, regarding the establishment of the various college bureaus in Paris. This series also includes information on the American University Union in Europe, of which the CSB was a part. About thirty American colleges founded the Union to "aid all American college men in any form of service abroad." (Quotation taken from circular on the Union in the Bureau's Nettleton correspondence)
  - American University Union--Circulars, Clippings and Reports, 1917-1924 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - American University Union
    - Constitution and Budget, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1919-1934 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Meetings, 1917-1921, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence--A through S, 1917-1919, (6 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 4 to 9)
  - Correspondence--Anson Phelps Stokes, T through Z, 1917-1919, (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 1 to 2)
  - Donations and Expenses, 1918-1919 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - General, 1918-1924, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Series III: Columbia War Hospital, 1914-1922
  These records include correspondence, some minutes and reports, and general information regarding the establishment of the hospital, supplies, and administrative issues. Most of the correspondence is with Dr. Francis Carter Wood (Professor of Cancer Research and member of the administrative board of the School of Dentistry) and Samuel Lambert (Dean of the College of Physicians and Surgeons). The College of Physicians and Surgeons was instrumental in the creation of the hospital. See also the oversize folder "Collections Oversize-World War I Collection-Newspaper Clippings" for an illustrated article in The New York Times' Mid-week Pictorial, 1917.
  - Correspondence--A through Y, 1917-1919, 1922, (4 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 5 to 8)
  - General Information, 1917, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Related Information, 1914-1917, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Supplies, 1917, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Series IV: Committee on Women's War Work, 1917-1919
  Series IV includes correspondence, lists, meeting minutes, and bulletins related to the University's attempts to organize women for the war effort. The University created the Committee for Women's War Work on April 10, 1917, with Virginia Newcomb as an instrumental member. By the end of the 1916-1917 academic year, the Committee "furnished 790 women for volunteer work and 25 for salaried positions." (1917 Annual Report, p.5) The Committee sent out enrollment cards to gather names of women interested in participating in the war. With this information, the Committee looked to place women in both volunteer and salaried positions. The University also created specific courses to train women in areas necessary to the war effort. Also included in this series is a separate card file box (Box 7) with membership cards the Committee asked women to fill out. At the front of the box is a sample instruction card. The card file is incomplete and only contains cards for surnames from A to Col.
  - Correspondence and Finances, 1917-1918 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - General Information, 1917-1919, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Information Bulletins, 1917-1918 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1917-1918 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Related Organizations and Information, 1917-1918, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Weekly Bulletins, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Series V: Instruction and Training, 1916-1923
  Series V consists of correspondence, enrollment cards, and general information on the various efforts by the University to train and instruct students for entry into the war. Included are folders on the Columbia Battalion as well as war-related courses and the war topography course syllabi. The folder "Columbia Battalion" contains mostly correspondence regarding preparation for the presentation of both the American flag and the Battalion flag to the Battalion on May 29, 1917. The folder also contains correspondence on the formation of the Battalion.
  - Subseries V.1: General, 1917-1923
    Contains general information on Columbia University's efforts to introduce and instruct students for engagement in the war.
    - Columbia Battalion, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Columbia University Naval Unit, 1917-1918 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Reserve Officers Training Corps, 1917-1923 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Signal Corps School of Photography, 1918-1919 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - United States Navy Gas Engine School--L.V. Hagman Notes, circa 1918 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - United States School of Military Cinematography, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - War Related Courses Offered at Columbia University, 1917-1919 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - War Topography Course--Notes, Syllabi and Related Materials, circa 1917, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 1 to 2)
  - Subseries V.2: Student Army Training Corps, 1918
    Consists of correspondence, which appears to be from the Office of the Secretary regarding the SATC as well as course information. Correspondence is filed alphabetically by surname. See also the oversized folder "Collections Oversize-World War I Collection-Student Army Training Corps" for advertising posters and schedules of courses.
    - Correspondence
      - A through Claxton, 1918 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Committee on Education and Special Training, 1918 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - F through MacCain, 1918 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - MacLaurin, 1918 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Man through W, 1918, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 7 to 8)
    - Course on Issues of the War, 1918 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Course on Issues of the War--Catalog of Books Used and Outline, 1918, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 1 to 2)
    - General Information, 1918, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Subseries V.3: Training Corps for Officers, 1916-1917
    Contains enrollment cards, which have valuable information on trainees. Also included are files for resignations, transfers, and assignments, arranged alphabetically by surname.
    - Assignments and Transfers, 1916-1917, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Enrollment Cards--A through F, 1917, (3 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 5 to 7)
    - Enrollment Cards--G through R, 1917, (5 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 1 to 5)
    - Enrollment Cards--S through Z, 1917, (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 1 to 2)
    - General Correspondence, 1917, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - General Information, 1917, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Lists, 1917, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Resignations, 1917 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Series VI: War Records Committee, 1915-1930
  The War Records Committee is comprised largely of correspondence and lists regarding the service of Columbia faculty, staff, students, and alumni in the war effort.
  - Subseries VI.1: Departments and Schools, 1915-1920
    Comprised of correspondence between the War Records Committee, Secretary's Office, and department and school heads regarding compilation of war service records of faculty and staff. A majority of the original folders had the names of professors on the outside of the folder. These lists of names have been photocopied and placed in the new folder. The folder "Civil Engineering, Department of" contains photographs of the Student Army Training Corps making a military map.
    - Agriculture, Department of, 1918-1919 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Architecture, School of, 1918-1919 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Botany, Department of, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Chemical Engineering, Department of, 1918-1919 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Chemistry, Department of, 1917-1919 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Civil Engineering, Department of, 1918, undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Classical Philology, Department of, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Diseases of Children, Department of, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Economics, Department of, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Electrical Engineering, Department of, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Engineer Drafting, Department of, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - English and Comparative Literature, Department of, 1917-1919 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Extension Teaching, Department of, 1917-1919 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Geology, Department of, 1917-1919 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Germanic Languages, Department of, 1917-1919 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - History, Department of, 1920 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Indo-Iranian Languages, Department of, undated (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Journalism, School of, 1917-1918 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Law, School of, 1916-1919 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Mathematics, Department of, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Mechanical Engineering, Department of, 1916-1919 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Metallurgy, Department of, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Mineralogy, Department of, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - Music, Department of, 1917-1919 (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - Neurology, Department of, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - Pharmacy, College of, 1917-1919 (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - Philosophy, Department of, 1917-1918 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Physicians and Surgeons, College of, 1917-1919, undated (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - Physics, Department of, 1918-1919, undated (Box 9, Folder 35)
    - Political Science, Faculty of, 1915-1919, undated (Box 9, Folder 36)
    - Psychology, Department of, 1917-1919 (Box 9, Folder 37)
    - Romance Languages, Department of, 1917-1919 (Box 9, Folder 38)
    - Slavonic Languages, Department of, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 39)
    - Sociology, Department of, 1918 (Box 9, Folder 40)
    - Teachers College, 1917-1919 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Zoology, Department of, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Subseries VI.2: Fraternities, 1917-1920
    Composed of correspondence between the War Records Committee and the various fraternities affiliated with Columbia regarding war service and memorial information for those who died while serving in the war. These records are arranged alphabetically by name of fraternity.
    - Alpha Chi Rho, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Alpha Delta Phi, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Alpha Phi Delta, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Alpha Sigma Phi, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Beta Theta Pi, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Delta Kappa Epsilon, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Delta Phi, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Delta Psi, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Delta Tau Delta, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Delta Upsilon, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Kappa Nu, 1918-1920 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Phi Delta Theta, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Phi Epsilon Pi, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Phi Gamma Delta, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Phi Kappa Psi, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Phi Kappa Sigma, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Phi Lamda Upsilon, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Phi Sigma Delta, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Phi Sigma Kappa, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Pi Lamda Phi, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Psi Upsilon, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - Sigma Alpha Epsilon, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - Sigma Alpha Mu, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 25)
    - Sigma Chi, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 26)
    - Sigma Nu, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - Theta Delta Chi, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 28)
    - Theta Xi, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - Zeta Beta Tau, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 30)
    - Zeta Psi, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Subseries VI.3: Alumni Classes, 1917-1920
    Consists of correspondence regarding war service records between Ruth Woodbridge (Clerk of the War Records Committee) and members of particular alumni classes. Correspondence folders are followed by folders of class lists. Usually Woodbridge asked one person to proofread the information and then pass it along to the remaining members of the alumni class.
    - Applied Science, School of
      - Correspondence
        - Class of 1881, 1917 (Box 10, Folder 32)
        - Class of 1903, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 33)
        - Class of 1904, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 34)
        - Class of 1908, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 35)
        - Class of 1910, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 36)
      - Lists--Classes of 1901-1917, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 37)
    - Architecture, School of--Correspondence--Class of 1900, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 38)
    - Columbia College
      - Correspondence
        - Class of 1883, 1917-1918 (Box 10, Folder 39)
        - Class of 1900, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 40)
        - Class of 1904, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 41)
        - Class of 1905, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 42)
        - Class of 1906, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 43)
        - Class of 1907, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 44)
        - Class of 1909, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 45)
        - Class of 1911, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 46)
        - Class of 1913, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 47)
        - Class of 1916, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 48)
        - Class of 1917, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 49)
      - Lists--Classes of 1901-1909, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 50)
      - Lists--Classes of 1910-1919, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Fine Arts--Lists--Classes of 1901-1919, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Law, School of
      - Correspondence
        - Class of 1900, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 3)
        - Class of 1901, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 4)
        - Class of 1902, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 5)
        - Class of 1904, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 6)
        - Class of 1909, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 7)
        - Class of 1910, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 8)
        - Class of 1911, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 9)
        - Class of 1912, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 10)
        - Class of 1915, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 11)
        - Class of 1916, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 12)
        - Class of 1917, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 13)
      - Lists--Classes of 1903-1919, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Physicians and Surgeons, College of
      - Correspondence
        - Class of 1889, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 15)
        - Class of 1890, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 16)
        - Class of 1891, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 17)
        - Class of 1893, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 18)
        - Class of 1895, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 19)
        - Class of 1898, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 20)